{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This political party was created by the Tamworth Manifesto, which aimed to distinguish it from the Duke of Wellington’s government. A leader of this party gave the Winds of Change speech in South Africa, signaling decolonization that included this party’s suppression of the Mau Mau Rebellion. A leader of this party nicknamed “Milk Snatcher” won a war over the Falklands Islands, and it allied with the DUP in 2016 under Theresa May. For ten points, name this British political party opposed by the Labour Party.",
      "answer": "Conservative Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man served as the second and final U.S. Secretary for Foreign Affairs. This man once joked that he could travel through the country by the lights of people burning him in effigy after he negotiated a treaty that provided for the removal of British troops from forts in the Northwest Territory. This author of five of the Federalist Papers is this namesake of a 1795 treaty with Great Britain. For ten points, name this first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.",
      "answer": "John Jay"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s name derives from the Algonquin word for “trading,” since Philemon Wright founded a timber trade here that defined this city’s early economy. This city was originally divided into Upper and Lower Towns in accordance with a plan laid out by John By, who also designed the Rideau Canal that services this city. This city forms a metropolitan area with nearby Gatineau, and is the site of Parliament Hill. For ten points, name this city in Ontario, the capital of Canada.",
      "answer": "Ottawa"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Ottoman Empire first conquered this modern-day country by defeating the forces of Tuman Bay II at the Battle of Ridaniya. A Muslim state based in this country was ruled by the Bahri and Burji Dynasties. Muhammad Ali declared himself Khedive of this country under the Ottoman Empire, and established this country’s cotton industry. The capital of the Mamluk Sultanate was in, for ten points, what country that has been ruled from the cities of Fustat and Cairo?",
      "answer": "Egypt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. This policy was first reported in 2002 by The Hill and made news again in March 2017 in an Ashley Parker profile of the former Karen Batten. This policy’s ideological precedent is the Modesto Manifesto, leading some reporters to dub it the Billy Graham Rule. Critics of this policy, which includes rules regarding alcohol, work, and dining partners, argue that its application in the Governor’s office in Indianapolis and the White House constitutes sexual discrimination. For ten points, identify this personal code of the Vice President.",
      "answer": [
        "Mike Pence’s rules regarding behavior with women",
        "descriptions of Mike Pence’s rule against dining alone with women who aren’t his wife, Pence’s rule against working late with women, and/or Pence’s rule against attending events with alcohol without his wife being present"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This scientist disproved Lavoisier’s definition of acids being elements that contain oxygen. This man injured himself while working with nitrogen trichloride, which led to him hiring Michael Faraday as an assistant. This scientist experimented on himself with nitrous oxide, realizing that it could be used as an anesthetic that he nicknamed “laughing gas.” For ten points, name this English scientist who discovered elements like calcium, iodine, and chlorine.",
      "answer": "Sir Humphry Davy"
    },
    {
      "question": "These places are required to tolerate, but not promote, disagreeable speech due to the case Hazelwood v. Kuhlmeier. The speech rights of black-armband wearing people in one of these places was the subject of the case Tinker v. Des Moines. Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg ruled that these places could be desegregated via busing. For ten points, name these public institutions whose “separate but equal” status was banned by Brown v. Board of Education.",
      "answer": [
        "public schools",
        "answers related to elementary, middle, and/or high schools",
        "do not",
        "answers related to colleges",
        "universities"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Because Richard Lawrence believed that he held this position, he attempted to assassinate president Andrew Jackson and was thereafter confined to an insane asylum. FDR held a publicized hot dog dinner with the holder of this position in June, 1939. John Dickinson was the primary author of a document addressed to the holder of this position, which urged him to reconsider tax provisions over the American colonies. For ten points, the Olive Branch Petition was addressed to the holder of what position, George III?",
      "answer": [
        "King of England",
        "equivalents such as the British monarch"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A Frank Gehry-designed memorial to this man controversially plans to include a tapestry of stainless steel cables, which may depict peaceful imagery of France or Kansas. Statues planned for this man’s memorial include a group inspired by a photo of this man instructing the 101st Airborne Division on June 5th, 1944. In 2017, officials celebrated the groundbreaking of a long-planned memorial for, for ten points, what Supreme Commander of Allied Forces during World War II and US President?",
      "answer": "Dwight D. Eisenhower"
    },
    {
      "question": "Descriptionacceptable.Duringthisevent,theCRSpreventedcitizensfromcrossingariver;theythen built barracades instead. Daniel Cohn-Bendit [ben-deet] led one faction during this event, in which the president claimed “nobody attacks an empty palace” before fleeing the country. The Grenelle Agreements attempted to resolve this event, which was preceded by the Movement of 22 March, whose members occupied a portion of Nanterre. Protests at the Arc de Triomphe and the Sorbonne were a part of, for ten points, what massive period of civil unrest in France in the late 1960s?",
      "answer": [
        "May 1968 student protests or",
        "any two of the three underlined parts of “student protests against Charles de Gaulle in May 1968”"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scandal was carried out by middlemen Adnan Khashoggi and Manucher Ghorbanifar. As part of this scandal, secretary Fawn Hall shredded evidence of violations of the Boland Amendment. This scandal was investigated by the Tower Commission and led to indictments for Caspar Weinberger and John Poindexter, who had aided in the funding of an anti-Sandinista force abroad. For ten points, name this Reagan-era scandal in which funds from arms sales to the Middle East were redirected to aid rebels in Nicaragua.",
        "answer": "Iran-Contra scandal or affair, etc."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fawn Hall worked for this Marine lieutenant colonel, who was charged with 16 felonies for destroying evidence. However, all charges against this man were either dropped or vacated, as he was granted immunity for Congressional testimony.",
        "answer": "Oliver “Ollie” North"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, Charles Hay’s troops toasted his enemies and asked them to fire first; Maurice de Saxe prevailed over the Duke of Cumberland in that Battle of Fontenoy. Disagreements over whether Charles VI could violate Salic law in proclaiming his heir helped prompt this war, which began when Silesia was invaded by Frederick the Great of Prussia. For ten points, name this 1740 war over Maria Theresa’s succession to a Habsburg throne.",
        "answer": "War of the Austrian Succession"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shortly after the War of the Austrian Succession, the alliances shifted in this event, triggered by statesman Anton von Kaunitz. As a result of this event, France allied with Austria and Britain allied with Prussia.",
        "answer": "Diplomatic Revolution"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this conflict, Henri Huet [en-ree oo-ay] photographed a silhouetted corpse falling out of a helicopter. A sculpture commemorating this war by Frederick Hart shows three soldiers of different ethnicities in U.S. Army and Marine Corps uniforms. That sculpture stands near another commemoration of this war, built after its designer won a contest; that memorial is engraved with over 50,000 names. For ten points, name this war for which Maya Lin built a Veterans Memorial wall.",
        "answer": "Vietnam War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A photo of Mary Ann Vecchio weeping over a body was taken at an anti-Vietnam War protest at this Ohio university.",
        "answer": "Kent State University"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event began when Lucius Cimber presented a petition to return his brother from exile. Security forces failed to reach this event in time, even though Servilius Casca had leaked its details. This event triggered the Liberator’s Civil War, in which the perpetrator Cassius was hunted down by the Second Triumvirate. Outside the Theater of Pompey, this event’s target may have cried “et tu, Brute?” [broo-tay] as he was stabbed. For ten points, name this 44 BC event in which a dictator of Rome was killed.",
        "answer": "assassination or murder, stabbing, etc. of Julius Caesar"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Caesar’s death was avenged at this 42 BC battle in Macedonia, where an alliance of Marc Antony and Octavian compelled the defeated Brutus to commit suicide.",
        "answer": "Battle of Philippi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jews living under this empire were recruited into cantonist schools and forced to complete years of military service. Menahim Beilis was accused by this empire’s officials of murdering a young boy and dumping his body near a brick factory, as related in Bernard Malamud’s novel The Fixer. The Pale of Settlement was created to house Jews by a female ruler of this empire. For ten points, name this empire which allowed some Jews to serve on the Duma under Nicholas II.",
        "answer": "Russian Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Pale of Settlement on Russia’s western frontier included all of this modern Baltic state, where over 100,000 people were killed by the Nazis in Ponary Forest near Vilnius.",
        "answer": "Lithuania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Near the end of this film, a man indicates his support for the main character by wiping the sweat off of his brow using his handkerchief. Lily James portrays a secretary in this film whose primary job is to type dictated letters and speeches. In this film, Viscount Halifax threatens to resign his cabinet position unless the Prime Minister agrees to peace talks with Nazi Germany. For ten points, name this 2017 film set in May 1940, named for a famous speech of Winston Churchill.",
        "answer": "Darkest Hour"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This legendary British actor reportedly burned through - literally - a $20,000 cigar budget while portraying Winston Churchill in Darkest Hour. This man’s past disparaging remarks about the Golden Globes didn’t prevent him from winning their Best Actor in a Drama award in 2018.",
        "answer": "Gary Oldman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first of these conflicts was triggered by crackdowns against the Gio and Mano ethnic groups. In another of these conflicts, the LURD rebel group shelled the capital until the Accra Peace Agreement was signed. The first of these conflicts led to the capture and murder of Samuel Doe, and the second led to Gyude Bryant leading a transitional government until the election of Ellen Johnson Sirleaf. Charles Taylor rose to power after the first of these wars and was exiled after the second. For ten points, name this pair of internal conflicts that rocked Monrovia.",
        "answer": [
          "Liberian Civil Wars",
          "descriptions of civil fighting in Liberia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the Second Liberian Civil War, LURD allied themselves with the Kamajors hunter unit from this country, located immediately northwest of Liberia.",
        "answer": "Sierra Leone"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This period was mitigated by the creation of shelterbelts by the Forestry Service. This period received its name after Robert Geiger’s visit to Boise City on the Sunday of April 14 coincided with an incidence of “black blizzards.” Dorothea Lange’s photograph Migrant Mother became symbolic of this period’s mass displacement of “Okies” who traveled to California after facing crop failure. For ten points, name this period of the 1930s in which severe drought affected the American plains.",
        "answer": "Dust Bowl"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This singer became known as the “Dust Bowl troubadour” after composing a series of ballads that included Pretty Boy Floyd. This man, whose guitar “kills fascists,” also wrote “This Land is Your Land.”",
        "answer": "Woodrow “Woody” Guthrie"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Western Expansion",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Third US President, who bought the Louisiana Purchase.",
          "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Territory, now a state with capital Salem, whose northern border was disputed with Britain.",
          "answer": [
            "Oregon Territory",
            "state"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Concept,whosenamewascoinedbyJohnSullivan,thatarguedwesternexpansionwasapredetermined right.",
          "answer": "Manifest Destiny"
        },
        {
          "question": "1862 act that gave western settlers land plots if they farmed the land for five years.",
          "answer": "Homestead Act of 1862"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which the French and Indian War ended and a Proclamation banning expansion beyond the Appalachians was issued.",
          "answer": "Proclamation of 1763"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name given to those who settled Oklahoma Unassigned Lands before the official proclamation.",
          "answer": "Sooners"
        },
        {
          "question": "Historian whose Frontier Theory argued that American democracy developed through western expansion.",
          "answer": "Frederick Jackson Turner"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican-American war general whose namesake code governed the New Mexico territory and who served as military governor of California.",
          "answer": "Stephen Kearney"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Council of Trent",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Church, led by popes, that convened the Council.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholic Church"
        },
        {
          "question": "Movement, led by Martin Luther, that the Council sought to address.",
          "answer": "Protestant Reformation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holy Roman Emperor who demanded a council be held, some 20 years after he sacked Rome.",
          "answer": [
            "Charles V",
            "Charles I of Spain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of rites, including Baptism and the Eucharist, that the Council re-affirmed.",
          "answer": "seven sacraments"
        },
        {
          "question": "Latin translation of the Bible that was named the official canon at the Council.",
          "answer": "Vulgate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fourth century saint who created most of that Latin translation of the Bible.",
          "answer": "Saint Jerome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lutheran concept that “works” are not necessary to receive God’s pardon.",
          "answer": "justification by faith alone or sola fide"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope who originally convened the Council in 1545.",
          "answer": "Paul III"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Brazil",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Continent divided by the Treaty of Tordesillas, which organized Brazilian colonization.",
          "answer": "South America"
        },
        {
          "question": "National language of Brazil, as a result of its European colonization.",
          "answer": "Portuguese"
        },
        {
          "question": "Businessman who established a company town in Brazil to produce rubber for his company’s Model T’s.",
          "answer": "Henry Ford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Practice partially ended by the Law of the Free Womb and fully ended by the Golden Law.",
          "answer": "slavery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last Emperor of Brazil. He led Brazil to victory in the War of the Triple Alliance.",
          "answer": "Dom Pedro II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Substance that, with milk, names a period of rule by landowners in Sao Paulo and Minas Gerais.",
          "answer": [
            "coffee or caf´e",
            "caf´e com leite politics, rule, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader who established Brazil’s Estado Novo regime in 1930.",
          "answer": "Getulio Vargas"
        },
        {
          "question": "1851-52 war in which Brazil defeated the Juan Manuel de Rosas-led Argentine Confederation to gain power over a major river basin.",
          "answer": "Platine War"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this event, Lieutenant Braunersreuther [brown-ers-roy-ter] demanded a surrender within 30 minutes and received it 29 minutes later. At the outset of this event, Captain Henry Glass was surprised to find only a Japanese merchant ship in port. The victims of this event, lacking proper guns in (20 pts)",
        "Fort Santa Cruz, rowed to the USS Charleston to verbally return what they thought was a salute, because they were unaware that the US had (10 pts)",
        "declared war on Spain. Only warning shots were fired during, for ten points, what bloodless 1898 event in which a western Pacific island changed hands?"
      ],
      "answer": "capture or invasion, attack, surrender, etc. of Guam during the Spanish-American War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An essay by Simone Weil claims that the central theme of a poem by this author is unbridled force and power. According to a tradition known as the Certamen, Hesiod won a bronze tripod in a (20 pts)",
        "poetry contest against this man. Richmond Lattimore is best known for his translations of this man’s works, one of which begins by describing the rage of (10 pts)",
        "Achilles when his concubine is seized by Agamemnon. For ten points, name this blind Greek poet who wrote about the Trojan War in the Iliad."
      ],
      "answer": "Homer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this region, tunnels painted to look like black anthracite were claimed to be coal mining tunnels rather than invasion routes. This region was the site of a “flagpole war” where countries competed to have taller flags. The Bridge of (20 pts)",
        "No Return was used for prisoner exchanges in this region, which includes a (10 pts)",
        "Joint Security Area in what was the village of Panmunjom. For ten points, name this region along the 38th parallel that was created in the Armistice of 1953 to separate warring nations on an Asian peninsula."
      ],
      "answer": "Korean Demilitarized Zone or DMZ"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city declared Jesus Christ its king in the aftermath of the War of the League of Cognac. Luca Pitti called for an armed revolt against Piero the (20 pts)",
        "Gouty in this city to avoid paying off his debt. Michele [mik-ay-lay] di Lando was the first leader of a group of angry wool workers in this city during the Revolt of the (10 pts)",
        "Ciompi. Sixtus VI said he was unable to sanction, but nevertheless appreciated, the Pazzi conspiracy to depose this city’s ruling family. Lorenzo the Magnificent ruled, for ten points, what Italian city, home to the Medicis?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Florence",
        "Firenze"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man analyzed whether watching a specially-curated episode of the show Medical Center would trigger anti-social behavior in participants. A mind-body thought experiment by this thinker imagines a human being serving as an interlocutor for another’s thoughts; this thinker called those beings (20 pts)",
        "“cyranoids.” The trial of Adolf Eichmann inspired another one of this thinker’s experiments, some variants of which were conducted at a nearby warehouse rather than at a (10 pts)",
        "Yale laboratory. For ten points, name this social psychologist who encouraged unknowing participants to administer shocks under the orders of an authority figure."
      ],
      "answer": "Stanley Milgram"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this nation was militarily supported by the Safari Club in fighting the first Shaba conflict. Another leader of this country was executed by a firing squad commanded by Moises (20 pts)",
        "Tshombe; that ruler was deposed after calling in Soviet aid to suppress the secession of its Katanga provinces. Another leader of this country tried to promote (10 pts)",
        "“authenticit´e” by wearing the abacost and renaming his country Zaire. For ten points, name this country once ruled by Patrice Lumumba and Mobutu Sese Seko from Kinshasa."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Democratic Republic of the Congo",
        "DRC",
        "Zaire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A man with this surname was supported by a group of New Hampshire college students who shaved and showered. The initiative “Clean for Gene” supported (20 pts)",
        "Eugene, a 1968 Democratic candidate with this surname from Minnesota. The Tydings Committee investigated claims made by a senator with this surname, including that the (10 pts)",
        "State Department contained numerous “loyalty risks” and “card carrying communists.” For ten points, give this surname of Wisconsin senator Joseph, a leading figure in the 1950s Red Scare."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "McCarthy",
        "Eugene McCarthy",
        "Joseph McCarthy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A key site of fighting during this battle was the Wo¨evre [wheh-vre] plain, where the Germans overran Fort Vaux [voh] after having captured Fort Douaumont with little resistance. Thousands of men and vehicles were shuttled along the (20 pts)",
        "Sacred Way to this battle, where Erich von Falkenhayn wanted to inflict the maximum number of casualties on the (10 pts)",
        "French. Phillipe Petain’s leadership earned him the epithet “the Lion of,” For ten points, what 1916 battle along the Meuse River, the longest of World War I?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
    }
  ]
}